Guide to the Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) Records TAM.633
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) Records
1963-1967
TAM.633
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.5 linear feet Two boxes
Collection includes fragile onion skin typing paper and newsprint.
Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), one several New York City chapters of the CORE national organization, was formed in March 1963, and remained active until the end 1966. Founders included Rita and Michael Schwerner (the latter one of the group of three civil rights workers murdered in Philadelphia, Mississippi in 1964), and members included well-known leftist and radical pacifist activists, such as Murray Bookchin and Igal Rodenko. The chapter focused on tenant organizing, combatting racial discrimination in housing and the exclusion of nonwhites from building trades unions. Women members of Downtown CORE who were arrested in a demonstration and had served jail terms at New York City’s Women’s House of Detention organized a campaign to reform the prison. Most of the materials in the collection concern conditions in New York City’s Women’s House of Detention or racial discrimination in housing in New York City. Organizations represented in the collection include Downtown CORE, the Human Rights Commissions of New York City and State, the National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing, Committee of Outraged Parents, and the national CORE office. Documents include letters to the editors of New York City newspapers and New York City public officials, memoranda to New York City Mayor John V. Lindsay, spiral bound notebooks with handwritten notes, newspaper clippings and newspapers, circulars, press releases, policy statements, reports, leaflets, and posters, mainly between the years 1963 to 1965.
Congress of Racial Equality.
Appraisal note
No records were removed from this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This collection was a gift from Dr. Helena Lewis in 2013. The accession number associated with this gift is 2013.012.
Scope and Contents note
Collection consists of documents from [New York City] Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), the Human Rights Commissions of New York City and State, the National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing, Committee of Outraged Parents, and the national CORE office, mainly between the years 1963 to 1965. These include handwritten notes, handwritten drafts and carbon copies of typed correspondence addressed to New York City public officials and letters to the editors of New York City newspapers, circulars, newspaper clippings, memoranda to New York City Mayor John V. Lindsay; press releases, policy statements, reports, leaflets, spiral bound notebooks with handwritten notes, and posters.
Most of these documents concern conditions in New York City’s Women’s House of Detention (reports on, protests against, and proposals for remediation, and racial discrimination in housing in New York City, including reports on discriminatory practices by specific real estate agents garnered through “testing” (sending a white person, followed by an African American person to attempt to rent the same apartment and comparing their treatment by the agents). Correspondents include: Helena Lewis (aka Helena Levine), Benita Cannon, Barbara Pliskow and Carol Janeway. One of the circulars by the Committee of Outraged Parents focuses on the experiences of poet Andrea Dworkin (then an 18-year-old freshman at Bennington College) arrested in a protest against the war in Vietnam and held in the Women’s House of Detention.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open to users without restriction.
Historical/Biographical Note
Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), a chapter of the CORE national organization, was formed in March 1963 and remained active until the end 1966. Based on Manhattan’s Lower East Side, it was one of nearly a dozen New York City local chapters organized in the early 1960s. Its founders included Rita and Michael Schwerner (the latter one of the group of three civil rights workers murdered in Philadelphia, Mississippi in 1964), and its members included radical pacifist Igal Rodenko, anarchist activist and theorist Murray Bookchin, and writer Bell Gale Chevigny.
While the chapter focused much of its energy on tenant organizing and combatting racial discrimination in housing, its first local action, in July and August of 1963, was organizing demonstrations protesting discrimination in hiring of workers building Rutgers Houses (a public housing development then under construction on the Lower East Side), as part of a national CORE campaign against all-white building trades unions. A dozen and half Downtown members were arrested on disorderly conduct charges during these demonstrations and sentenced to five days in prison or paying a $25 fine. Three of them, including Helena Lewis (sometimes also known as Helena Levine), an administrative assistant at New York University and a Downtown CORE officer, refused to pay their fines and served their time at New York City’s Women’s House of Detention, in October 1964. Appalled by what they saw and experienced there, they mounted a campaign, in concert with others, to protest and focus public attention on conditions at the prison. This campaign included sending letters to editors of newspapers and confidential memoranda to New York City and State public officials, and testifying to a grand jury convened (possibly in part because of their actions) to investigate complaints against state of affairs at the jail, as well as to the New York State legislature's Joint Committee on Penal Institutions.
Bibliographical Note
Information for this guide was drawn in part from the website, "CORE NYC: A History of the New York City Chapters of the Congress of Racial Equality" (http://corenyc.org/index.htm), section on Downtown CORE (http://corenyc.org/downtowncore.htm).
Committee of Outraged Parents.; Lewis, Helena, Dr.; National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing.; Discrimination in housing.; Prisons |z United States.; Reformatories for women; Reformatories for Women |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Container List
  - Conditions in New York City Women's House of Detention -- Letters to Editors and Public Officials, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conditions in New York City Women's House of Detention -- Notes; Letters to Editors and Public Officials, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conditions in New York City Women's House of Detention -- Letters to Editors, Memoranda to Public Officials, Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee of Outraged Parents, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing, 1964, ca 1960s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Downtown CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) -- Actions and Strategies Against Racial Discrimination in Housing, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - New York City Commission on Human Rights and New York State Commission on Human Rights - Pamphlets, Press Releases, Policy Statements, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York City and National CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), 1963,1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)